<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gallienus redivivus, or, Murther will out, &amp;c. being a true account of the de-witting of Glencoe, Gaffney, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13102060</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13102060</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47745)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 744:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gallienus redivivus, or, Murther will out, &amp;c. being a true account of the de-witting of Glencoe, Gaffney, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Charles Leslie. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Glencoe Massacre, 1692.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97420:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97420:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Gallienus Redivivus, OR, <hi>Murther Will Out.</hi> &amp;c. Being a True Account of the DE-WITTING OF Glencoe, Gaffney, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <p>They gave out that the deſign of their Coming was to introduce <hi>Liberty,</hi> and depoſe <hi>Tyrants:</hi> But having gain'd the Power, They did ſo <hi>Tyrannize</hi> Themſelves, That the Reign of Former Oppreſſors ſeem'd a Golden Age, if compar'd with the <hi>Arbitrarineſs</hi> and <hi>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ction</hi> of theſe pretended <hi>DELIVERERS;</hi> which made the <hi>Sicilians</hi> think them much more happy, who Expir'd in <hi>Servitude,</hi> than thoſe who liv'd to ſee ſuch a <hi>DISMAL FREEDOM.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Plutarch.</hi> Life of <hi>Timoleon.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> in the Year 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97420:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97420:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A LETTER from a Gentleman in <hi>SCOTLAND</hi> to his Friend at <hi>LONDON,</hi> who deſir'd a Particular Account of the Buſineſs of <hi>GLENCO.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Edinburgh, <date>
                           <hi>April.</hi> 20th 1692.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE Account you deſir'd of that ſtrange and ſurprizing Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre of <hi>Glenco,</hi> take as follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mac-jan Mac-donald,</hi> Laird of <hi>Glenco,</hi> a Branch of the <hi>Mack-donalds,</hi> one of the greateſt Clans (or Tribes) in the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> came with the moſt Conſiderable Men of his Clan to Coll. <hi>Hill,</hi> Governour of <hi>Fort William</hi> at <hi>Inverlochy,</hi> ſome few days before the Expiring of the time for receiving the Indemnity appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Proclamation, which as I take it, was the Firſt of <hi>January</hi> laſt, entreating he would adminiſter unto him the <hi>Oaths</hi> which the foreſaid Proclamation requir'd to be taken; that ſo ſubmitting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Government, he might have its Protection. The Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel receiv'd him with all Expreſſions of Kindneſs; nevertheleſs ſhifted the adminiſtring the <hi>Oaths</hi> to him, alledging that by the Proclamation it did not belong to him, but to the Sheriffs, Bailyffs of Regalities, and Magiſtrates of Burghs, to adminiſter them. <hi>Mac-jan</hi> Complaining that by this <hi>Diſappointment</hi> he might be wrong'd, the Time being now near the Expiring, and the Weather ſo extreme, and the Ways ſo very bad, that it was not poſſible for him ſo ſoon to reach any Sheriff, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> got from Coll. <hi>Hill,</hi> under his Hand, his Protection; and withal he was aſſur'd, that no Orders from the Government againſt him ſhould be put in Execution, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he were firſt advertis'd, and had time allow'd him to apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to King or Council for his own Safety. But the better to make all ſure, (tho' this might have ſeem'd Security enough for that time) with all diſpatch imaginable he poſted to <hi>Inverary,</hi> the Chief Town of <hi>Argylaſhire,</hi> there he found Sir <hi>Collin Camphel</hi> of <hi>Ardkinlis,</hi> Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff of that Shire, and crav'd of him the Benefit of the Indemnity, according to the Proclamation, he being willing to perform all the Conditions requir'd. Sir <hi>Collin</hi> at firſt ſcrupled to admit him to the Oaths, the Time which the Proclamation did appoint being elapſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by one day, alledging it would be of no uſe to him then to take
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97420:3"/>
them: But <hi>Mac-jan</hi> repreſented that it was not his Fault, he hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come in time enough to Collonel <hi>Hill,</hi> not doubting but he could have adminiſtred the Oaths to him, and that upon his refuſal he had made ſuch haſt to <hi>Inverary,</hi> that he might have come in time enough, had not the extremity of the Weather hinder'd him; and even as it was, he was but one day after the Time appointed; and that would be very unbecoming the Government to take Advantage of a Man's coming late by one Day, eſpecially when he had done his utmoſt to have come in time. Upon this, and his threatning to proteſt againſt the Sheriff for the Severity of this Uſage, he admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to him and his Attendants the Oaths, <hi>Mac-jan</hi> depending upon the Indemnity granted to thoſe who ſhould take them; and having ſo done, he went home, and lived quietly and peaceably un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Government, till the day of his Death.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>January</hi> laſt, a Party of the Earl of <hi>Argile's</hi> Regiment came to that Country, the Deſign of their coming was then ſuſpected to be to take courſe with thoſe who ſhould ſtand out, and not ſubmit, and take the Oaths. The Gariſon of <hi>Inverlochy</hi> being throng'd, and <hi>Glenco</hi> being Commodious for Quartering, as being near that Gariſon, thoſe Soldiers were ſent thither to Quarter; they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended they came to exact Arrears of Ceſs and Hearth-Money, (a Tax never known in <hi>Scotland,</hi> until laid on by the Parliament, 1690, after the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> had eas'd themſelves of it;) e er they entred <hi>Glenco,</hi> that Laird, or his Sons, came out to meet them, and asked them if they came as Friends, or as Enemies? The Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers anſwer'd, as Friends; and gave their Paroll of Honour, that they would do neither him nor his Concerns any harm; upon which he welcom'd them, promiſing them the beſt Entertainment the Place could afford. This he really perform'd, as all the Soldiers confeſs. He and they lived together in mutual Kindneſs and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip fifteen days, or thereabouts; ſo far was he from fearing any Hurt from them. And the very laſt Day of his Life he ſpent in keeping Company with the Commander of that Party, Capt. <hi>Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> of <hi>Glenlyon,</hi> playing at Cards with him till 6 or 7 at Night, and at their parting mutual Proteſtations of Kindneſs were renew'd. Some time that very day, but whether before or after their part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I know not, Capt. <hi>Campbell</hi> had theſe Orders ſent him from Major <hi>Duncanſon,</hi> a Copy whereof I here ſend you.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Ballacholis,</hi> 
                        <date>Feb. <hi>12. 1692.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> are hereby ordered to fall upon the Rebels the <hi>Mac-Donalds</hi> of <hi>Glenco,</hi> and put all to the Sword under <hi>70.</hi> You are to have eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecial Care, that the Old Fox and his Sons do upon no account eſcape your
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97420:3"/>
Hands; You are to ſecure all the Avenues, that no Man eſcape: This you are to put in Execution at five a Clock in the Morning preciſely, and by that time, or very ſhortly after it, I'll ſtrive to be at you with a ſtronger Party. If I do not come to you at five, you are not to tarry for me, but to fall on. <hi>This is by the King's SPECIAL COMMAND,</hi> for the Good and Safety of the Country, that theſe Miſcreants may be cut off, Root and Branch. See that this be put in Execution without Feud or Favour, elſe you may expect to be Treated as not true to the King or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, nor a Man fit to carry Commiſſion in the King's Service. Expecting you will not fail in the fulfilling hereof, as you love your ſelf. I ſubſcribe theſe with my Hand,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Robert Duncanſon.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>For Their Majeſties Service, to Capt. <hi>Robert Campbell</hi> of <hi>Glenlyon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Duncanſon</hi> had receiv'd Orders from Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> which were as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Ballacholis,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Feb. 12. 1692.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PER</hi> Second to the Commander in Chief, and my Collonel's Orders to me, for putting in Execution the Service commanded againſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels in <hi>Glenco,</hi> wherein you, with the Party of the Earl of <hi>Argyle</hi>'s Regiment under your Command are to be concern'd: You are therefore forthwith to order your Affairs ſo, as that the ſeveral Poſts already aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd you, be by you and your ſeveral Detachments fallen in Action with, preciſely by five a Clock to morrow Morning, being <hi>Saturday;</hi> at which time I will endeavour the ſame with thoſe appointed from this Regiment for the other Places. It will be moſt neceſſary you ſecure thoſe Avenues on the South ſide, that the Old <hi>Fox,</hi> nor none of his Cubs get away. The Orders are that none be ſpar'd, from <hi>70,</hi> of the Sword, nor the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment troubled with Priſoners. This is all, until I ſee you. From</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your humble Servant. <hi>James Hamilton.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>Pleaſe to order a Guard to ſecure the Ferry, and the Boats there; and the Boats muſt be all on this ſide the Ferry, after your Men are over.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>For their Majeſties Service, for Major <hi>Robert Duncanſon,</hi> of the Earl of <hi>Arg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le</hi>'s Regiment.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97420:4"/>
                  <p>THE Soldiers being diſpoſed five or three in a Houſe, according to the Number of the Family they were to Aſſaſſinate, had their Orders given them ſecretly. They had been all receiv'd as Friends by thoſe poor People, who intending no Evil themſelves, little ſuſpected that their Gueſts were deſign'd to be their Murtherers. At 5 a Clock in the Morning they began their bloody Work, Surpris'd and Butcher'd 38 Perſons, who had kindly receiv'd them under their Roofs. <hi>Mac-jan</hi> himſelf was Murther'd, and is much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n'd; He was a ſtately well-favour'd Man, and of good Courage and Senſe: As alſo the Laird <hi>Archintrikin,</hi> a Gentleman of more than ordinary Judgment and Underſtanding, who had ſubmitted to the Government, and had Coll. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Protection in his Pocket, which he had got three Months before. I cannot without Horror repreſent how that a Boy about Eight Years of Age was murthered; he ſeeing what was done to others in the Houſe with him, in a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Fright run out of the Houſe, and eſpying Capt. <hi>Campbell,</hi> graſp'd him about the Legs, crying for Mercy, and offering to be his Servant all his Life. I am informed Capt. <hi>Campbell</hi> inclined to ſpare him; but one <hi>Drummond,</hi> an Officer, barbarouſly run his Dagger through him, whereof he died immediately. The rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of ſeveral Particulars and Circumſtances of this Tragical Story, makes it appear moſt doleful; as that <hi>Mac-jan</hi> was killed as he was drawing on his Breeches, ſtanding before his Bed, and giving Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to his Servants for the good Entertainment of thoſe who mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered him; While he was ſpeaking the Words, he was ſhot through the Head, and fell dead in his Ladies Arms, who through the Grief of this and other bad Uſages ſhe met with, died the next day. It is not to be omitted, that moſt of thoſe poor People were killed when they were aſleep, and none was allowed to pray to <hi>God</hi> for Mercy. Providence ordered it ſo, that that Night was moſt boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; ſo as a Party of 400 Men, who ſhould have come to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther End of the <hi>Glen,</hi> and begun the like Work there at the ſame Hour, (intending that the poor Inhabitants ſhould be encloſed, and none of them eſcape) could not march at length, until it was 9 a Clock, and this afforded to many an Opportunity of eſcaping, and none were killed but thoſe in whoſe Houſes <hi>Campbell</hi> and <hi>Glenlyon</hi>'s Men were Quartered, otherwiſe all the Male under 70 Years of Age, to the Number of 200, had been cut off, for that was the Order; and it might have been eaſily executed, eſpecially conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Inhabitants had no Arms at that time; for upon the firſt hearing that the Soldiers were coming to the <hi>Glen,</hi> they had conveyed them all out of the way; For though they relyed on the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97420:4"/>
promiſes which were made them for their Safety; yet they thought it not imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>obable that they might be diſarmed. I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to impute it to difficulty of diſtinguiſhing the Difference of a few Years, or to the Fury of the Soldiers, who being once glutted with <hi>Blood,</hi> ſtand at nothing, that even ſome above Seventy Years of Age were deſtroyed. They ſet all the Houſes on Fire, drove off all the Cattle to the Gariſon of <hi>Inverlochy, viz.</hi> 900 Cows, 200 Horſes, and a great many Sheep and Goats, and there they were divided amongſt the Officers And how diſmal may you imagine the Caſe of the poor Women and Children was then! It was lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, paſt expreſſion; their Husbands and Fathers, and near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations were forced to flee for their Live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; they themſelves almoſt ſtript, and nothing left them, and their Houſes being burnt, and not one Houſe nearer than ſix Miles; and to get thither they were to paſs over Mountains, and Wreaths of Snow, in a vehement Storm, wherein the greateſt part of them periſhed through Hunger and Cold. It fills me with horror to think of poor ſtript Children and Women, ſome with Child, and ſome giving Suck, wreſtling againſt a Storm in Mountains, and heaps of Snow, and at length to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and give over, and fall down, and die miſerably.</p>
                  <p>You ſee in <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s Order to <hi>Duncanſon,</hi> there's a ſpecial Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>That the Old Fox nor none of his Cubs ſhould eſcape;</hi> and in <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canſon</hi>'s Order to Capt. <hi>Campbell</hi> of <hi>Glenlyon, That the old Fox nor none of his Sons eſcape;</hi> but notwithſtanding all this wicked Caution, it pleas'd God that the two young Gentlemen, <hi>Mac-jan</hi>'s Sons e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcap'd. For it happened that the younger of theſe Gentlemen truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed little to the fair Promiſes of <hi>Campbell,</hi> and had a more watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eye over him than his Father or Brother, who ſuffered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by his reiterated Oaths to be deluded into a belief of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity: He having a ſtrong Impreſſion on his Spirit, that ſome miſchievous <hi>Deſign</hi> was hidden under <hi>Campbell</hi>'s ſpecious <hi>Pretences,</hi> it made him, after the reſt were in Bed, remain in a retired Corner, where he had an advantagious Proſpect into their Guard. About midnight perceiving ſeveral Soldiers to enter it, this encreaſed his Jealouſy; ſo he went and communicated his Fears to his Brother, who could not for a long time be perſwaded there was any bad <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign</hi> againſt them, and Aſſerted, That what he had ſeen, was not a doubling their Guards in order to any ill deſign, but that being in a ſtrange place, and at a diſtance from the Gariſon, they were to ſend our Centinels far from the <hi>Guard,</hi> and becauſe of the Extremity of the Weather relieved them often, and that the Men he ſaw could be no more but theſe. Yet he preſiſting to ſay, That they were not ſo ſecure, but that it was fit to acquaint their Father with what
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97420:5"/>
he had ſeen, he prevailed with his Brother to riſe, and go with him to his Father, who lay in a Room contiguous to that they were in. Though what the younger Son alledged made no great Impreſſion on his Father, yet he allowed his Sons to try what they could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. They well knowing all Skulking places there, went and hid themſelves near to a Centinel's Poſt, where inſtead of one they diſcovered eight or ten Men; this made them more inquiſitive, ſo they crept as near as they could without being diſcovered, ſo near that they could hear one ſay to his Fellows, That <hi>he liked not this Work, and that had he known of it he would have been very unwilling to have come there; but that none, except their Commanders, knew of it till within a quarter of an hour.</hi> The Soldier added, That he was willing to fight againſt the Men of the <hi>Glen,</hi> but it was baſe to murder them. But to all this was anſwered, <hi>All the blame be on ſuch as gave the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; we are free, being bound to obey our Officers.</hi> Upon hearing of theſe words, the young Gentlemen retired as quickly and quietly as they could towards the Houſe, to inform their Father of what they had heard; but as they came nigh to it they perceived it ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded, and heard Guns diſcharged, and the People ſhrieking; whereupon, being unarm'd, and totally unable to reſcue their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they preſerved their own Lives in hopes yet to ſerve their King and Country, and ſee Juſtice done upon thoſe Hell-Hounds, treacherous Murtherers, the <hi>Shame</hi> of their Country, and <hi>Diſgrace</hi> of Mankind.</p>
                  <p>I muſt not forget to tell you, That there were two of theſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers who had given their Paroll of Honour to <hi>Mac-jan,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to be concerned in that <hi>Brutal Tragedy,</hi> for which they were ſent Priſoners to <hi>Glaſco,</hi> where if they remain not ſtill, I am ſure they were ſome Weeks ago.</p>
                  <p>Thus, Sir, in obedience to your Commands, I have ſent you ſuch Account as I could get of that monſtrous and moſt inhuman Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre of the Laird of <hi>Glenco,</hi> and others of his <hi>Clan.</hi> You deſire ſome Proofs of the truth of the Story; for you ſay there are many in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> who cannot believe ſuch a thing could be done, and publick Juſtice not executed upon the Ruffians: For they take it for granted, that no ſuch Order could be given by the Government; and you ſay they will never believe it without a downright Demonſtration. Sir, As to the Government, I will not meddle with it; or whether theſe Officers who murdered <hi>Glenco,</hi> had ſuch Orders as they pretended from the Government; the Government knows that beſt, and how to vindicate their own Honour, and puniſh the Murtherers who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended their Authority, and ſtill ſtand upon it. But as to the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact of the Murther of <hi>Glenco,</hi> you may depend upon it, as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97420:5"/>
certain and undeniable: It would be thought as ſtrange a thing in <hi>Scotland</hi> for any Man to doubt of it, as of the death of my Lord <hi>Dundee,</hi> or with you that the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> loſt his Head. But to put you out of all doubt, you will e'er long have my Lord <hi>Argyle</hi>'s Regiment with you in <hi>London,</hi> and there you may ſpeak with <hi>Glenlyon</hi> himſelf, with <hi>Drummond</hi> and the reſt of the Actors in that diſmal Tragedy; and on my Life, there is never a one of them will deny it to you; for they know that it is notoriouſly known all over <hi>Scotland,</hi> and it is an Admiration to us that there ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one in <hi>England</hi> who makes the leaſt doubt of it. Nay, <hi>Glenlyon</hi> is ſo far from denying it, that he brags of it, and juſtifies the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on publickly: He ſaid in the Royal Coffee-Houſe in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> that he would do it again; nay, That he would ſtab any Man in <hi>Scotland</hi> or in <hi>England,</hi> without asking the Cauſe, if the King gave him Orders, and that it was every good Subject's duty ſo to do; and I am credibly inform'd, that <hi>Glenlyon</hi> and the reſt of them have addreſs'd themſelves to the Council for a Reward for their good Service, in deſtroying <hi>Glenco,</hi> purſuant to their Orders.</p>
                  <p>There is enough of this mournful Subject: If what I have ſaid ſatisfy you not, you may have what farther Proof, and in what manner you pleaſe to ask it.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your humble Servant,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <label>N. B.</label> 
               <hi>That the Gentleman to whom this Letter was ſent, did on</hi> Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, June 30. 1692. <hi>when the Lord</hi> Argyle<hi>'s Regiment was quartered as</hi> Brentford, <hi>go thither, and had this Story of the Maſſacre of</hi> Glenco <hi>from the very Men who were the Actors in it:</hi> Glenlyon <hi>and</hi> Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond <hi>were both there. The Highlander who told him the Story, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Guilt which was viſible in</hi> Glenlyon, <hi>ſaid, Glenco</hi> hangs about <hi>Glenlyon</hi> Night and Day, and you may ſee him in his Face. <hi>I am told likewiſe that Sir</hi> John Lowther <hi>refuſed to accept of the Place of Lord Advocate of</hi> Scotland, <hi>unleſs he might have liberty to proſecute</hi> Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyon, <hi>and the reſt of the Murtherers of</hi> Glenco, <hi>which not being grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> James Stuart (<hi>who was ferfeited for Treaſon by K.</hi> C. 2. <hi>and ſince Knighted by K.</hi> W.) <hi>has now the Place.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97420:6"/>
            <head>Gallienus Redivivus: OR, <hi>Murther Will Out,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE fore-going Account of the Barbarous <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of <hi>Glenco,</hi> was Printed in the year 1692. in the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to Dr. <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Book</hi> of the <hi>State of the Proteſtants in Ireland:</hi> And all the Reception it met with among many here in <hi>England,</hi> was, That it was a <hi>Jacobite</hi> Story, on purpoſe to Reflect upon the Government, and that there was no ſuch thing: But this is now Confuted by the Proceedings of the Parliament in <hi>Scotland,</hi> this Summer Seſſion, 1695. Wherein they have Voted the Killing of the <hi>Glenco-men</hi> to be a Murthrr; and yet have Acquitted Sir <hi>Thomas Levingſton,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Hill,</hi> who gave the Orders for Killing of them. Why? Becauſe their Orders were but purſuant to the <hi>Inſtructions</hi> they had from <hi>Court.</hi> Where will this Lodge the <hi>Murther?</hi> The Deſign, it is well enough known, is to put it upon Sir <hi>John Dalrymple,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call'd <hi>Maiſter of Stair,</hi> one of the <hi>Secretaries</hi> for <hi>Scotland,</hi> becauſe he is not ſo <hi>Fiery a Presbyterian</hi> as the other Secretary, <hi>James Johnſton,</hi> who hath it by <hi>Inheritance</hi> to love <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Mitre</hi> alike; and to have a juſt Reward for it. But <hi>Dalrymple</hi> is only a <hi>Libertine,</hi> or <hi>Latitudinarian,</hi> One of the Modern <hi>No-Religion,</hi> who are <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> to <hi>All,</hi> ſo they be <hi>troubled</hi> with <hi>none.</hi> Therefore he cares not whether <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> or <hi>Presbytery,</hi> or what elſe is ſet up, provided the People be eaſy with it.</p>
            <p>NOW it being known to all the World, That the Pretence of the <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which was made the Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work for aboliſhing <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and ſetting up <hi>Presbytery</hi> there, was a meer <hi>Sham,</hi> contriv'd by this <hi>Johnſton,</hi> and the BIGOT <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> Party in <hi>Scotland;</hi> who were all put in Power, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this <hi>Revolution;</hi> and ſet on the <hi>Barbarous Rabbling</hi> of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97420:6"/>
               <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy</hi> in the <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that they might Cry out, The <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> were againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy:</hi> And having, by theſe and other Arts (which are fully related in Print) <hi>Pack'd,</hi> and then <hi>ſurpriz'd</hi> the firſt <hi>Convention,</hi> or <hi>meeting of Eſtates,</hi> to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh <hi>Epiſcopacy:</hi> They dare not have a New <hi>Parliament</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Quercla Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> p. 8 and 9.</note> (as in <hi>England</hi>) but keep on the ſame <hi>Convention</hi> (only Changing the Name into that of a <hi>Parliament</hi>) to this day: Becauſe no <hi>Free Parliament</hi> can be had in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which would not the firſt day, ſpue out <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and Re-Eſtabliſh their much more belov'd <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> And the People ſhewing great Un-eaſineſs under their preſent E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment (which hath been <hi>trick'd</hi> and <hi>forc'd</hi> upon them.) All the <hi>Craft</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> of the <hi>Regnant Presbytery,</hi> aſſiſted by <hi>Acts of Parliament,</hi> and all the Countenance of the <hi>Government,</hi> having not yet been able to Ouſt the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or prevail with the <hi>People</hi> to admit of, or almoſt give Civil Treatment to the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters</hi> ſent to them, tho' <hi>Eſtabliſh'd by Law.</hi> The <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Intereſt ſtanding there up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo ſlender a bottom, their <hi>Juncto</hi> think it not ſafe to have a Man of <hi>Dalrymple</hi>'s <hi>Latitude</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> in ſo eminent a Poſt, and near their King; leſt he ſhould follow the <hi>Inclinations of the People,</hi> in GOOD EARNEST, and Call a New <hi>Parliament</hi> there, which would ruine all their Meaſures: Therefore ways and means muſt be uſed to Remove him; and leave <hi>Johnſton</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterian Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> in the ſole Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Court.</hi> At length, this of <hi>Glenco</hi> was pitch'd upon; which was ſo Odious, They knew their <hi>King</hi> durſt not own it: And therefore they would throw it upon <hi>Dalrym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> who was Secretary, and attended when the <hi>Inſtructions</hi> were ſent for that <hi>Bloody Murther.</hi> And thereby too, They would ſeem to take off the <hi>Odium</hi> from their <hi>King;</hi> This was their pretence; and they had proof enough againſt <hi>Dalrymple:</hi> But how that Clear'd his <hi>Maſter</hi> will be ſeen.</p>
            <p>THEY produced <hi>Nine</hi> Letters of <hi>Dalrymple</hi>'s (of which I have Copies) concerning the <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of <hi>Glenco.</hi> And I ſhall have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to mention them hereafter; I will now ſet down their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Dates,</hi> and <hi>Directions;</hi> and quote them to ſave Repetition, only by their Number, Letter i. ii. iii. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The two firſt are directed to Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and bear Date, on the 1ſt. and the other the 3d. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1691. the 4 next are to Sir <hi>Thomas Levingſton,</hi> of theſe ſeveral Dates, 7, 9, 11 and 16 of <hi>January</hi> 1691/2;. Then follow two more to Collonel <hi>Hill,</hi> of the 16th and 30th of the ſame Month; And laſtly one of the 30th Ditto, to Sir <hi>Thomas Levingſton.</hi> It ſeems very ſtrange that K. W. would ſuffer theſe Letters to be expos'd to the Parliament in <hi>Scotland,</hi> being moſt of them wrote
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97420:7"/>
by his Order, enlarging upon, and enforcing the Execution of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions,</hi> ſent with them for the <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of <hi>Glenco,</hi> &amp;c. and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard which his <hi>Dear Presbyterians,</hi> and his Favourite <hi>Johnſton,</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, had to his Honour, was very ſlender, when, to compaſs their Ends, they load him ſo fouly, that they might load <hi>Dalrymple</hi> too. <hi>Johnſton</hi> ſays, <hi>No,</hi> But that he <hi>foreſeeing</hi> (becauſe ſome ſay of his own <hi>Contriving</hi>) that the <hi>Parliament</hi> (who are moſt of them his <hi>Creatures,</hi> to their Honour be it ſpoken) would fall upon the buſineſs of <hi>Glenco;</hi> and that they muſt be, at leaſt <hi>ſeemingly</hi> Gratified in it, otherwiſe that it might obſtruct the <hi>Money-Bills,</hi> did therefore, adviſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to ſend down a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to men of his own chooſing, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the Affair of <hi>Glenco;</hi> but withal, to give <hi>ſecret Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to his <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> to keep up the ſaid <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> unleſs the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould enter upon that buſineſs. And if they did, then to produce the ſaid <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> to ſhew his Majeſty's <hi>Innocence,</hi> by his <hi>Care</hi> to have it Examined; and withal, it would take the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of it out of the hands of <hi>Parliament Committees,</hi> who might not manage ſo dextrouſly, as thoſe of his own naming.</p>
            <p>THINGS being thus ſtated, and the neceſſary Orders given it is vilely ſuſpected, that <hi>Johnſton</hi> procured the Matter to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> whereby, at once, to get rid of his <hi>Rival</hi> Secretary, and Root up the intereſt of any, who had but an indifferency to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> at <hi>Court;</hi> though to the utter <hi>Shipwrack</hi> of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>'s Honour, to be Recorded for all <hi>Poſterities</hi> (as if it were inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable from ſome Conſtitutions to <hi>betray</hi> thoſe they ſerve, even tho' they wiſh them well, and muſt ſtand and fall with them.) For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the inflence <hi>Johnſton</hi> had in that <hi>Parliament,</hi> and that they have never yet oppos'd his Will in any thing; and that he has been able to ſuppreſs the leaſt <hi>Murmur,</hi> or <hi>Hint,</hi> that looked, towards <hi>Glenco,</hi> when the Fact was New Committed; and the <hi>Horror</hi> of it <hi>freſh</hi> and <hi>Bleeding;</hi> and now for three years after. I ſay, It is not ſuppoſed by men who underſtand that Parliament, that it could have been brought upon the Stage, when it was almoſt dead and forgotten, if the hand of <hi>Joab</hi> had not been in it: but let him look to that—I have only to add, as a Completion of the fore-going <hi>Narative,</hi> that I can from unqueſtionable Vouchers, give the Reader an Account of the Orders from Court to Sir <hi>Thomas Levingſton,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Hill,</hi> which are not in the <hi>Letter</hi> that goes before; and when the Reader is told that <hi>Hamilton</hi> (whoſe Order to <hi>Duncanſon</hi> is inſerted) had his Order from <hi>Levingſton,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Hill;</hi> Then he has the whole thread, <hi>viz.</hi> W. R's Order to <hi>Levinſton,</hi> and <hi>Hill; Levingſton</hi> and <hi>Hill</hi> to <hi>Hamilton; Hamilton</hi> to <hi>Duncanſon;</hi> and <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to <hi>Glenlyon,</hi> who was the <hi>Butcher:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97420:8"/>
               <hi>and ſubſcrib'd by Himſelf.</hi>— And to ſhew how pleaſing a thing <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> was to them, and with what reluctancy they Proſecuted thoſe who had not taken the Oaths, he ſays in the ſame Letter; <hi>Juſt now</hi> Argyle <hi>tells me, That</hi> Glenco <hi>hath not taken the Oaths, at which</hi> I Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce. <hi>It's a great work of</hi> Charity <hi>to be exact in Rooting out that Damnable Sect.</hi> And to ſhew how great this <hi>Charity</hi> was, and whence it proceeded, The <hi>Wiſe</hi> Secretary Blurts out theſe words; <hi>I have no great kindneſs for</hi> Keppoch, <hi>nor</hi> Glenco, <hi>and it's well theſe People are in mercy.</hi> Well indeed! They were in <hi>merciful</hi> hands! Who can ſay they ought not to Die, for whom ſuch a Secretary hath no CREAT <hi>Kindneſs!</hi> But who are they muſt die? ALL! ALL! Man, Woman, and Child! <hi>Maſſacre</hi> the <hi>Men,</hi> and Drive the <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> to Periſh more cruelly in the Mountains. To which purpoſe, that extreme <hi>Cold</hi> Seaſon was choſen for the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> i.</note> 
               <hi>The Winter is the only Seaſon</hi> (ſays the Secretary) <hi>in which we are ſure the</hi> High-Landers <hi>cannot eſcape us, nor carry their Wives, Bairns, and Cattle to the Mountains.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> ii.</note> 
               <hi>It's the only time that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Eſcape you; for Human Conſtitution cannot endure to be long out of Houſes— This is the proper Seaſon to maul them in the cold long Nights.</hi> This was expreſs'd with the Guſto of a <hi>Vulture,</hi> in expectation of a Glorious <hi>Maſſacre!</hi> And then how <hi>eaſy</hi> it would be!<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> iv.</note> 
               <hi>I expect</hi> (ſays he) <hi>you will find little Reſiſtance but from the ſeaſon.</hi> And then what thorough work they would make!<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> iii.</note> 
               <hi>To deſtroy entirely the Country of Lochaber, Lochells, Lauds, Keppoch's, Glengaries, Appin, and Glenco.</hi> Here was a plentiful Feaſt provided! It was a Raviſhing Proſpect!</p>
            <p>BUT O how theſe <hi>Lyons</hi> were Enraged when any of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Prey was delivered out of their Jaws. It was in a mournful ſtrain the Secretary tells the ſad News.<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> iv.</note> 
               <hi>We have an Account</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that</hi> Lochart, <hi>and</hi> Mac-naghton, Appin <hi>and</hi> Glenco <hi>took the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Indemnity at</hi> Inverary; <hi>and</hi> Keppoch, <hi>and others</hi> at Inverneſs: But after this, when <hi>Argyle</hi> told him that <hi>Glenco</hi> had not taken the <hi>Oaths;</hi> How did he <hi>Rejoyce!</hi> as above Quoted.<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> ix.</note> 
               <hi>I am glad</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that</hi> Glenco <hi>did not come in within the time preſcribed.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> i</note> 
               <hi>I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that</hi> CLAN <hi>except it ſelf.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> iv.</note> 
               <hi>For my part, I could have wiſh'd the</hi> Mac-donalds <hi>had not divided,</hi> (that is, That they had all excluded themſelves from mercy) <hi>and I am ſorry that</hi> Keppoch, <hi>and</hi> Mac-jan <hi>of</hi> Glenco <hi>are ſafe.</hi> But it ſeems they were not ſafe. Some muſt be made a <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> And <hi>Glenco</hi> was pitched upon for the <hi>Victim.</hi> And the <hi>implacable Fury,</hi> which was ſhewn againſt that <hi>Clan,</hi> expreſſed the Rage they felt, that ſo many had eſcaped them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>Clan</hi> was to be <hi>deſtroyed entirely.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> iii.</note> 
               <hi>I aſſure you</hi> (ſays the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to his Officers) <hi>your Power ſhall be full enough, and I hope the Soldiers will not trouble the</hi> Government <hi>with Priſoners.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ii.</note> 
               <hi>For a juſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97420:8"/>
Example of Vengeance, I entreat that the Thieving Tribe in</hi> Glenco <hi>may may be Rooted out in earneſt.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> vii.</note> 
               <hi>I ſhall entreate you that for a juſt Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and publick Example, the Thieving Tribe of</hi> Glenco <hi>may be Rooted out to purpoſe. The Earl of</hi> Argyle <hi>and</hi> Broadalban <hi>have promiſed they ſhall have no Retreat in their Bounds; the Paſſes to</hi> Rannach <hi>would be ſecured, and the Hazard certified to the</hi> Laird <hi>of— to Retreat: Then in that Caſe</hi> Argyle's <hi>Detachment, with a Party that may be Poſted in</hi> Iſland Stalker, <hi>muſt cut them off.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> viii.</note> 
               <hi>Pray when any thing concerning</hi> Glenco <hi>is reſolved, let it be ſecret and ſudden, otherwiſe the Men will ſhift you, and better not meddle with them than not to do it to puropoſe, to cut off that Neſt of Robbers, who are fallen in the mercy of Law.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> ix.</note> 
               <hi>I am glad</hi> Glenco <hi>did not come in within the time Preſcribed. I hope what is done there may be in earneſt, ſince the reſt are not in a Condition to draw together to help. I think to herry their Cattle, or burn their Houſes, is but to render them Deſperate Lawleſs Men, to Rob their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: But I believe you will be ſatisfied it were a great Advantage to the Nation, That that Thieving Tribe were Rooted out, and Cut off. It muſt be Quietly done, otherwiſe they will make ſhift for</hi> both <hi>the Men and their Cattle.</hi> Argyle's <hi>Detachment lies in</hi> Keppoch <hi>well, to aſſiſt the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to do all</hi> ON A SUDDEN. Was ever ſo greedy a Hunt after the Lives of a Company of <hi>Secure</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n arm'd</hi> People, who ſlept fearleſs, and ſuſpecting no danger; under the Protection of thoſe who were thus Contriving to <hi>Maſſacre</hi> them, in the moſt <hi>Savage</hi> and <hi>Treacherous</hi> manner!</p>
            <p>The <hi>Secretary</hi> tells Collonel <hi>Hill,</hi> that<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> viii.</note> 
               <hi>The Oaths are Indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> This was a fearful Method of Impoſing the Oaths upon theſe <hi>High Landers,</hi> that none muſt live who would not take them! But were All admitted to take them? One would think ſo; when they were made <hi>Indiſpenſable.</hi> Yet notwithſtanding, in that ſame Letter, He gives theſe Directions to Coll <hi>Hill. Till we ſee what is done by the</hi> CHIEFS, <hi>it is not time to Receive their Tenants, or</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting <hi>them to take the Oaths, or hoping for Pardon, 'till they give E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence that they are willing to pay their Rents to you, and to take Tacks for their former Duties; who will not do ſo, and were in the Rebellion, muſt feel the diſmal Conſequences of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THUS <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard made him a Blaſphemer! If the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants would betray the Rights of their Land-Lords to Atturn and Pay their Rents to the <hi>Secretary,</hi> or his <hi>Governour,</hi> then, and not otherwiſe, They ſhould be <hi>Admitted</hi> to take the <hi>Oaths:</hi> And yet they muſt not live, if they did not take the <hi>Oaths;</hi> But <hi>Glenco</hi> took the <hi>Oaths;</hi> yet that ſav'd not his <hi>Life,</hi> nor his <hi>Clan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IT were reaſonable here to preſume that <hi>K. W.</hi> did not know that they had taken the <hi>Oaths. Firſt,</hi> If it had been ſo, This manner
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97420:9"/>
of <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> in <hi>Cold Blood</hi> had been a <hi>Cruelty</hi> without Precedent <hi>Secondly,</hi> It was taking Advantage of the Time, with the Greateſt Rigour. For the Time limited by the <hi>Indemnity</hi> expired but the 1ſt of <hi>January</hi> 1691/2. And the <hi>Inſtructions</hi> for a <hi>General Maſſacre</hi> were dated the 11th of the ſame Month, at <hi>London,</hi> which was hardly time enough to know whether they had taken the <hi>Oaths</hi> or not. But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Here is no room left to ſurmiſe, that <hi>K. W.</hi> did not know it; becauſe Secretary <hi>Dalrymple</hi> (in his Letter to Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Levingſton,</hi> before Quoted, which is dated at <hi>London</hi> the 9th of <hi>January,</hi> 1691/2) tells him<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> iv.</note> That they had an Account that <hi>Glenco</hi> had taken the <hi>Oaths,</hi> at <hi>Inverary;</hi> which was the Place where he did take them, as is told in the foregoing Narrative. And he tells Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> in the ſame Letter; <hi>I have been with the King. He ſays your Inſtructions ſhall be diſpatched on Monday.</hi> And they were ſo For that <hi>Monday</hi> was the 11th of <hi>January,</hi> 1691/2. which day the <hi>Inſtructions</hi> do bear Date. And this Letter of the <hi>Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s was Dated the 9th of <hi>January,</hi> 1691/2. which was the <hi>Saturday</hi> before. And then he tells Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> That he had the Account of <hi>Glenco</hi>'s having taken the <hi>Oaths</hi> with ſeveral others; and that he had been with the <hi>King</hi> concerning it, and <hi>Inſtructions</hi> ſhould be ſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis true, his Letter of the 11th, which went with the <hi>Inſtructions,</hi> ſays.<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter</hi> v.</note> That <hi>Argyle</hi> told him <hi>Glenco</hi> had not taken the <hi>Oaths.</hi> But this was no more than <hi>Hearſay;</hi> and it was not true. For <hi>Glenco</hi> had taken the <hi>Oaths</hi> before that time; according to to the Account which the <hi>Secretary</hi> own'd was ſent to him: And <hi>Argyle</hi> was an Enemy to <hi>Glenco,</hi> as appears by what is above quoted out of Letter 7. But this ſaying of <hi>Argyle</hi>'s to the <hi>Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> could not be of <hi>Argyle</hi>'s own Knowledge. And one would think that the <hi>Secretary of State</hi> ſhould have as good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence as he.</p>
            <p>BUT, to make the moſt of it, this cou'd amount to no more than a <hi>Doubt.</hi> And to Suſpend his further Reſolution, till he might have the Certainty from <hi>Scotland.</hi> But they did not ſtay for this. For the particular Inſtructions to Maſſacre <hi>Glencoe,</hi> bore Date the 16th of <hi>January</hi> 1691/2 Betwixt which time and the 11th. when <hi>Argyle</hi> told the <hi>Secretary,</hi> as above, They could not ſend to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and have any Anſwer back. Now theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of the 16th were no way <hi>Conditional.</hi> To cut off <hi>Glencoe,</hi> if he had not taken the <hi>Oaths.</hi> But Poſitive, and without more ado. When it is certain that K. <hi>W.</hi> Muſt, at leaſt, <hi>Doubt</hi> whether he had taken the <hi>Oaths,</hi> or not. But it is apparent that Collonel <hi>Hill,</hi> who had Given <hi>Glencoe</hi> his <hi>Protection,</hi> and to whom <hi>Glencoe</hi> came to take the <hi>Oaths,</hi> I ſay it is certain that he, and the other Officers
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97420:9"/>
there upon the Place, knew very well that <hi>Glenco</hi> had taken the Oaths, and ſubmitted to the Government. Thoſe Officers whom he receiv'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Houſe, and quarter'd their Soldiers among his Tenants, upon his laying down his Arms; Theſe muſt know that he had <hi>Submitted.</hi> But if notwithſtanding they muſt Obey their Orders (as they did) if it be not Permitted to <hi>Officers,</hi> ſo much as <hi>Reſcribere,</hi> to acquaint the <hi>King</hi> with any miſtake may be in his <hi>Orders;</hi> but to Execute them blindfold, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Asking Queſtions, then let me lie out of the Reach of a Soldier.</p>
            <p>THE Reader muſt likewiſe know, that none of theſe Foreſaid <hi>Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> were Communicated to the <hi>Privy Council</hi> of <hi>Scotland;</hi> to whom by the Conſtitution of that Kingdom, and Continual Cuſtom, all the King's Orders are directed. They knew nothing of this Matter, It was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd to be Carry'd in ſuch a Manner, as not to be prevented. And when <hi>Gallienus</hi> his Thirſt of <hi>Blood</hi> is once Satisfy'd, then let <hi>Slaves</hi> Grumble, and make Inquiry! We know how to Manage them. <hi>Johnſton</hi> hath undertaken it. Nay he hath done it. <hi>Done it!</hi> More effectually than ever was heard, or I believe, <hi>Imagin'd,</hi> in theſe Nations, before this Happy <hi>Revolution:</hi> For here is a Precedent made, and that by <hi>P—t,</hi> That the King may ſend his Guards, and Cut any Man's Throat in the Nation in Cold Blood; Nay, he may Maſſacre the whole P—t, as they are there Sitting, by the Rule that they have given; That is, To acquit <hi>Leving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> and <hi>Hill;</hi> and to juſtify them for purſuing the <hi>King's Orders</hi> to Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre a whole <hi>Clan,</hi> which is no more Juſt, or Law, than to Maſſacre a P—t.</p>
            <p>LET us <hi>Banter</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> or our ſelves no more with Liberty and Laws! And when P— ts can be brought to Approve, and Juſtify All this—Well! <hi>Johnſton!</hi> Thou haſt Manag'd Nobly. Thou art fit to Serve a <hi>Monarch!</hi> But not unleſs you bring your Monarch cleverly off in this Buſineſs; For what if you can place it upon <hi>Dalrymple;</hi> And if <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rymple</hi> ſhould be Hang'd for Daring to ſend ſuch an Order, tho' he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to Counter-ſign it, What will become of <hi>Him,</hi> who both <hi>Sign'd</hi> it, and <hi>Counter-Sign'd</hi> it, and Commanded it to be <hi>Sent?</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>If the Man ſuch Praiſes have,</l>
               <l>What muſt He Employs the K—?</l>
            </q>
            <p>WHY! did his <hi>Maſter</hi> never Inquire into this Matter before? Never before the <hi>Parliament</hi> Clamour'd! And what was the Meaning of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Examine into what himſelf had Order'd— But <hi>Mes James!</hi>— And have you e'en brought your <hi>Maſter</hi> into this Nooſe! What can you expect from him, but to be <hi>Glen-Co'd</hi> for your pains? <hi>Qui Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat, Glencoabitur</hi>— You have brought all his Sins to Remembrance. The <hi>Dewitting</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> was almoſt forgot.— You have pretty good Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of his Temper, or you may have. But if he ſuffer you to live to ſee another <hi>Revolution,</hi> you may plead <hi>Merit:</hi> For all his Enemies have not render'd him ſo <hi>Black;</hi> ſo effectually <hi>Proved,</hi> and <hi>Demonſtrated</hi> it to the World, as your Management has done. <hi>He is happy in his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters!</hi> at leaſt very <hi>Juſtly</hi> ſerv'd by them!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97420:10"/>HE wants but a good <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> that he may not loſe his <hi>Character</hi> to after Ages. And <hi>Secretary,</hi> you cannot do better than to recommend your <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> to that Office. He'll do it <hi>Deliciouſly;</hi> he'll either find or make Parallels to him out of <hi>Antient Hiſtories</hi> (for he'll find none among the <hi>Modern,</hi> eſpecially in theſe <hi>Countries.</hi>) And make him (I'll warrant you) Excel them all. And among the reſt, I would recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend one to him, that fits the preſent Caſe ſo exactly, that you would think one was Copied out of the other, and it is as follows.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Gallienus,</hi> ut erat <hi>Nequam</hi> &amp; <hi>Perditus;</hi> ita etiam, ubi neceſſitas co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egiſſet, <hi>velox, furibundus, ferus, vehemens, Crudelis.</hi>—In omnes <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiacos</hi> tam <hi>Milites</hi> quam <hi>Cives</hi> aſperime Ceviit: Nec quemquam ſuae Crudelitatis exortem reliquit: Uſque adeo <hi>Aſper</hi> &amp; <hi>Truculentus</hi> ut pleraſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Civitates vacuas a virili ſexu relinqueret.</q>
            <q>Extat ſane Epiſtola <hi>Galieni</hi> quam ad <hi>Celerem Verianum</hi> Scripſit, qua ejus Nimietas crudelitatis oſtenditur: quam Ego idcirco interpoſui, ut omnes intelligerent, hominem Luxurioſum crudeliſſimum eſſe, ſi neceſſitas Poſtulet.</q>
            <p>GALLIENUS VERIANO. <hi>Non mihi ſatisfacies, ſi tantum</hi> Armatos <hi>occideris, quos &amp; ſors Belli interimere potuiſſet. Perimendus eſt</hi> omnis ſexus Virilis, <hi>ſi &amp;</hi> ſenes <hi>at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> Impuberes <hi>ſine Reprehenſione noſtra occidi poſſent. Occidendus eſt quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> malevoluit. Occidendus eſt quicum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> male dixit contra me, contra Valeriani filium, contra tot Principum Patrem &amp; Fratrem. Ingenuus factus eſt Imperator.</hi> Lacera Occide, concide: <hi>Animum meum intelligere potes, mea Mente iraſcere qui haec Manu mea ſcripſi.</hi> Trebell. Pollion. <hi>Trigint. Tyran. de Ingenuo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS is the Deſcrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of <hi>Gallienus,</hi> a <hi>Cruel,</hi> and a <hi>Bloody Tyrant:</hi> And here is the Copy of ſome <hi>Inſtructions</hi> he ſent to <hi>Verianus,</hi> an Officer of his, about juſt ſuch another <hi>Maſſacre</hi> as <hi>Glenco,</hi> which he Wrote, or <hi>Sign'd</hi> with his own Hand: Wherein he Commands him, to put all to the Sword, All that durſt <hi>Speak</hi> or <hi>Think</hi> againſt him, as well <hi>Old</hi> as <hi>Young;</hi> He bid him <hi>Plunder, Kill, Tear;</hi> and that it would not pleaſe him if he Kill'd only thoſe in <hi>Arms</hi> againſt him, but All of the <hi>Maſculine</hi> Sex.</p>
            <p>HERE was a Great deal of Do, and many Words about it! But our Milder Order, bid only EXTIRPATE, and that not this or that Body, or making Diſtinctions of <hi>Old</hi> or <hi>Young, Men</hi> or <hi>Women</hi>—What need all that Cookery! But only <hi>The Whole TRIBE. That was all!</hi> He Scorn'd to <hi>Except</hi> the pitiful <hi>Women,</hi> as <hi>Gallienus</hi> did. What need <hi>They</hi> be <hi>Excepted?</hi> Why! He Excepted no Body! Short Work's beſt— and Few Words— And as the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to Great <hi>Britains Juſt Complaint,</hi> Publiſh'd by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, 1692. Says, p. 37. in Vindication of <hi>W. R.</hi> as to this of <hi>Glenco. A milder Order was never given.</hi> And he ſays that his Majeſty <hi>has Expreſs'd a High Diſpleaſure at it.</hi> It was <hi>High</hi> indeed: For we never heard of it before. Nor are we like to hear of it, that I can ſee: For all the Officers who <hi>Commanded,</hi> or who <hi>Executed</hi> it, are ſtill in their Reſpective Poſts, unleſs Advanc'd. Nor have we heard that ſo much as an <hi>ill Word</hi> has been ſaid by Him to any one of them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:97420:10"/>BUT this we know, by that <hi>Anſwer</hi> to Great <hi>Britains Juſt Complaint,</hi> that <hi>W. R.</hi> cannot plead Ignorance, that there was a great Clamour about the Maſſacre of <hi>Glenco, Three Years ago:</hi> And that He has taken no No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it all this time; nor <hi>Now,</hi> tiil it was firſt Started in <hi>Parliament;</hi> And that then, what he did, was, as much as he could, to take it out of the hands of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and by all his Might and Main, to <hi>Stifle,</hi> or at leaſt to <hi>Baffle</hi> it. And that it has been <hi>Baffled.</hi> And this horrible Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is thereby made to the Guilt of that <hi>Murther;</hi> That whereas none were anſwerable for it before, except only <hi>Gallienus</hi> and his <hi>Verianus</hi>'s, with their Accomplices, it is now become a <hi>National</hi> Guilt (ſo far as the <hi>Parliament</hi> are the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of the <hi>People</hi>) by the <hi>Parliament</hi>'s making <hi>GALLIEN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S's Inſtructions</hi> ſufficient to <hi>Juſtify Verianus</hi> in his Execution of them: Whereby they <hi>juſtify</hi> the whole <hi>Murder</hi> and bring it upon their own <hi>Heads,</hi> and upon the <hi>Heads</hi> of their <hi>Children.</hi> For if <hi>Gallienus</hi> had no Power by <hi>Law,</hi> to ſend ſuch <hi>Inſtructions,</hi> they could be no <hi>Juſtification</hi> to <hi>Verianus:</hi> But now <hi>That Parliament</hi> has Voted that ſuch <hi>Inſtructions</hi> are a <hi>Juſtification</hi> of <hi>Verianus;</hi> and therefore they have yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>Gallienus</hi> has, by <hi>Law,</hi> a <hi>Power</hi> to ſend ſuch <hi>Inſtructions.</hi> And that they ought to be <hi>Obey'd.</hi> And then, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>NOR has our <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>England</hi> been behind that of <hi>Scotland</hi> in Sacrificing our <hi>Laws, Lives,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> to an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Deſpotick</hi> Power; and that not only to <hi>Orders</hi> Sign'd by <hi>Gallienus</hi> himſelf, but by <hi>Verianus,</hi> of his own head. Making us Double Diſtill'd <hi>Vaſſals; Slaves</hi> of <hi>Slaves!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND the inſtance which (among many others) I have to give of this, Exceeds even that of <hi>Glenco,</hi> in its having leſs Pretence, and acted with the greater face of <hi>Authority,</hi> and <hi>Solemnity.</hi> I mean the <hi>Prodigious unprecedented</hi> Manner of the <hi>Murther</hi> of <hi>Gaffney</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Lord <hi>Coningsby;</hi> For which he was impeach'd before the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Gentlemen of <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Eſtates;</hi> and of <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>generous</hi> Spirits; whoſe noble Reſentment to ſee their <hi>Laws</hi> ſo vilely trampled under foot by thoſe whom they had Invited thither to protect them, brought them hither in Perſon, to demand Juſtice from our <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> againſt <hi>Conings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> who was one of their <hi>Members.</hi> And that there could be nothing of Revenge in the Caſe, in behalf of the Perſon who was Murther'd, it's notorious; that <hi>Gaffney</hi> being a poor Fellow, a Servant to <hi>Sweetman</hi> (hereafter mention'd) and wholly unknown, I believe, to every one of the Gentlemen who proſecuted <hi>Coningsby;</hi> Beſides, He was a <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,</hi> and one of the <hi>Native Iriſh,</hi> upon both of which Accounts he could have the leſs ſhare of Intereſt with the <hi>Britiſh,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Proteſtants,</hi> who were then not wholly come out of a moſt bloody War againſt them; for <hi>Limerick</hi> as yet held out. And therefore theſe worthy <hi>Patriots,</hi> who came over from <hi>Ireland</hi> hither to proſecute <hi>Coningsby,</hi> could have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Incitement, but Love of their Country, and the Preſervation of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97420:11"/>
the <hi>Laws:</hi> But the Return they had, after a long and Expenſive Attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance as it was, <hi>Mortifying</hi> to themſelves, and ſadly <hi>Inſtructive</hi> to others will remain an Inſtance of <hi>Arbitrary Government</hi> not to be equall'd in <hi>former</hi> Ages, nor eaſily credible to the <hi>future.</hi> The Story, one would think ſhould not need being told in <hi>England,</hi> becauſe it was brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stage, before the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> and is in their <hi>Printed Votes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>YET, all that, is not, it ſeems, ſufficient to Publiſh it, at this time; not one in twenty of ſome ſort of People that I meet with, having ever heard of it, or have forgot it: And (as I have told of the Story of <hi>Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co</hi>) they call it a <hi>Jacobite</hi> Invention; and will hear no more of it.</p>
            <p>I will therefore preſent the Reader with the very Words of the <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> concerning <hi>Gaffney,</hi> which (with ſeveral others of other Inſtances of <hi>High Arbitrary</hi> Government) was exhibited by the Earl of <hi>Ballimont,</hi> and other <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> againſt the Lords Juſtices of <hi>Ireland</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> The ſaid Lord <hi>Coningsby,</hi> and Sir <hi>Charles Porter,</hi> both <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> in <hi>England</hi>) before the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> in the Winter Seſſion 1693. The <hi>Article</hi> concerning <hi>Gaffney</hi> is the 4th, and follows in theſe Words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lords Juſſices did, in Council, by word of mouth, Order one <hi>Gaffney</hi> to be Hanged, without Tryal, the Courts of Juſtice being then open, and who was at that time an Evidence againſt one</hi> Sweetman <hi>for the murther of Collonel</hi> Foulk's <hi>ſoldiers: But the ſaid</hi> Sweetman (<hi>giving all his real Eſtate to the value of about</hi> 200 <hi>l.</hi> per Annum, <hi>to Mr.</hi> Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liford, <hi>beſides the ſum of about</hi> 500 <hi>l. to Mr.</hi> Fielding, <hi>the ſaid Lords Juſtices Secretary, for being his Bayl) was never proſecuted for the ſaid murthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; and the ſaid</hi> Gaffney <hi>was immediately Executed, according to the ſaid verbal Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>NOW the Reader muſt know that every Tittle of the ſaid Charge was proved fully, and paſt all Contradiction. Captain <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> who is a Member of the <hi>Privy Council</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Declared that he was then ſitting at the <hi>Board;</hi> and that the Council were not adviſed with at all in it. That <hi>Sweetman's Eſtate, valued at 3000 l.</hi> was offer'd to him [Captain <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi>] on Condition that he would make intereſt to ſave <hi>Sweetmas</hi>'s Life. That Lord <hi>Coningsby,</hi> who gave the Orders for Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of <hi>Gaffney,</hi> was in ſo great haſt to have him diſpatch'd out of the way (for he was an Evidence againſt <hi>Sweetman</hi>) That he ordered a <hi>Provo,</hi> inſtead of any <hi>Legal</hi> Officer, to be Call'd into the Council-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber where <hi>Gaffney</hi> was Examin'd; And after having asked <hi>Gaffney</hi> three or four Queſtions, and that he poſitively denied his having any Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the ſaid Murther; Commanded the <hi>Provo</hi> to take him out and hang him up IMMEDIATELY: And the <hi>Provo</hi> making Anſwer, That it would take ſome time to make a Gallows; <hi>Coningsby</hi> anſwered ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Hang him upon the Carriage of a Gun;</hi> which was done IMMEDIATE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97420:11"/>OF all this <hi>Coningsby</hi> could not deny One Word before the <hi>Houſe of Commons:</hi> And all he ſaid in his own Vindication was, <hi>That if he had not hang'd</hi> Gaffney <hi>ſo, he could not have hang'd him at all.</hi> Which was true: For there was no Evidence againſt him, and therefore they would give him no <hi>Tryal.</hi> But why muſt <hi>Gaffney</hi> then be Hang'd? Becauſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth! Some Officers in the Army would have ſome body Hanged for the Murther of <hi>Foulk</hi>'s Soldiers: And <hi>Sweetman</hi> (in whoſe <hi>Backſide</hi> the Soldiers were buried, and their Coats found in his Houſe) had given 500 <hi>l.</hi> to the Lords Juſtices <hi>Secretary,</hi> and his Eſtate to another man in Power; but <hi>Gaffney</hi> was a <hi>Poor Rogue,</hi> and had nothing to give, and therefore it was fit he ſhould be hang'd. And Hang'd <hi>as he was,</hi> or <hi>not at all.</hi> As <hi>CONINGSBY honeſtly,</hi> but <hi>Impudently</hi> Confeſſed.</p>
            <p>BUT now comes the Aſtoniſhing Wonder. After all theſe things ſo plainly <hi>Proved</hi> and <hi>Confeſs'd,</hi> that the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> could not frame any manner of excuſe for <hi>Coningsby;</hi> but were forc'd to Vote the <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> Gaffney <hi>without Tryal, to be</hi> Arbitrary <hi>and</hi> Illegal; <hi>Yet that</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the ſtate of Affairs, <hi>They did not think fit to ground an Impeachment againſt the Lord</hi> Coningsby <hi>for the ſame.</hi> This is in the Printed Votes of the 29th of <hi>January,</hi> 1693. And it is an <hi>Original.</hi> What! Vote a Man <hi>guilty,</hi> and yet that he ſhall not be <hi>proſecuted!</hi> Why pray? Becauſe of the <hi>ſtate of Affairs.</hi> This is very <hi>general:</hi> And ſuch a <hi>pretence</hi> will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be wanting. But what was this <hi>State of Affairs,</hi> at that time? It was in the Winter 1690, When all <hi>Ireland,</hi> except only <hi>Limerick,</hi> was in the Obedience of <hi>K. W.</hi> when the <hi>Courts of Juſtice</hi> were open (as in the boveſaid <hi>Article</hi> againſt <hi>Coningsby</hi> is expreſs'd) and the <hi>Lords Juſtices</hi> and <hi>Council</hi> ſitting in Peace and Grandeur in <hi>Dublin.</hi> And what was it then <hi>cou'd</hi> or <hi>ought</hi> to have hindered giving that <hi>Poor</hi> Fellow <hi>a fair Tryal?</hi> Other Criminals were then Tryed, in the uſual form, and why not <hi>Gaff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney?</hi> How came the <hi>State of Affairs</hi> to reach him, more than any other? Unleſs you will ſay, that it did reach to many others: For it is expeſs'd in the Printed <hi>Addreſs</hi> of the Lords, Preſented to K. W. 9 <hi>March</hi> 1692. That not only <hi>Gaffney,</hi> but <hi>ſeveral others</hi> were Executed, without any <hi>Tryal</hi> whatſoever; And that there were <hi>Exorbitant Abuſes, great Miſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, and many Arbitrary and Illegal Proceedings there, within theſe four Years laſt paſt, as well ſince the determination of the War as before,</hi> which includes the whole Government ſince the <hi>Revolution,</hi> as well dure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Adminiſtration of <hi>Gallienus</hi> in Perſon, while he was there, as of his ſeveral <hi>Verianus</hi>'s in his Abſence. One of whom did, in <hi>Almanzor</hi> ſtrain, ſet up the High Prerogative, and Hector their <hi>Parliament</hi> in a manner unknown to former Ages: And without Precedent from any Lawful King that ever ſat upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne in that Kingdom. Which they have given us an Account of in Print; to try whether there was ſo much of the Spirit of <hi>Engliſh Liberty</hi> left in an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament as to Vindicate their own Privileges, in that <hi>Breach</hi> which was made upon them, thro' the ſides of the Parliament in <hi>Ireland,</hi> a Province of their own,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97420:12"/>
and may be reckoned a branch of the <hi>Engliſh Empire.</hi> But all in Vain! They had drunk ſo deep in the Cup of <hi>Slavery</hi> at Home, that they could take no notice of it Abroad. They have ſtopt their Ears cloſe againſt all Charmers upon that Subject, <hi>Charm they never ſo wiſely.</hi> They Call their <hi>Slavery,</hi> Liberty! And where then is the <hi>Remedy!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus poor <hi>Ireland</hi> was left without all hopes of Redreſs, to feed upon the Melancholy Reflection; that their <hi>Liberties</hi> have been much more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly violated by their <hi>Deliverers,</hi> than by all the inſtances which were ſo much as alledg'd againſt their <hi>Lawful</hi> King; And thence to learn for the future, how much Rebellion is a worſe <hi>Remedy,</hi> than the Diſeaſe of Tyranny (even when it is not made a pretence) and that it always Ends in a Heavier Tyranny: Becauſe there muſt go more Force to keep under <hi>New Acquiſitions,</hi> than Old <hi>Hereditary Rights.</hi> And if all the Sacred <hi>Bonds</hi> of Natural Allegiance, Fortified with the Religious Sanction of Oaths, and Taught and Inculcated upon Us, from our Infancy, as a Condition indiſpenſable to our <hi>Salvation;</hi> if all this, and all the Honour and Reputation which the World has juſtly affixed to <hi>Loyalty,</hi> with the Horror, and eternal Stain, upon the Name and Memory of <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Rebels,</hi> and all the Terrors of the Laws againſt <hi>Treaſon.</hi> If none (I ſay) Nor all of theſe Conſiderations, have weight enough to keep us in our Obedience to thoſe whom God, and the Conſtitution of our Country, have plac'd over Us, by a Divine as well as a Legal <hi>Right:</hi> How ſhould an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> ſecure our Duty, who has none of theſe Tyes, on his ſide; but All, and every One of them againſt Him? How ſhould, How can He do it, but by Corrupting our Repreſentatives in Parliament, ſo as to paſs all his Arbitrary Deſigns upon Us, in their Names; and when that fails him, by open <hi>Force?</hi> How otherwiſe as any one of them ever yet ſecured himſelf? Have we forgot our late <hi>Deliverers</hi> in <hi>Forty One?</hi> Will no Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſerve to make us Wiſe! No. Not when the time of our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is come! We ſhall then, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did before their Final De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction by the <hi>Romans,</hi> we do now as they did then, Obſtinately Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe all Offers of Mercy, for our Rebellion? and continue to provoke a Power, which we know too ſtrong for Us; and which we Confeſs, muſt, without a Miracle, be our Ruine: Yet we run on, truſting only to our <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair!</hi> And we have not only Delivered up our Money and our Lives, without Account; but what uſed to be Dearer to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, <hi>The Honour of England!</hi> Of which take this ſhort Inſtance inſtead of many more.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> made (and printed) an <hi>Addreſs,</hi> dated the 18th of <hi>February</hi> 1692. Wherein They mind <hi>their</hi> King of the Capitulation made in the Year 1678, by which it was agreed, <hi>That the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Commander and Officer, in every Degree is to Command any other Confederate Officer of the ſame Rank (except thoſe of Crowned Heads) without any regard to the Date of their reſpective Commiſſions. And that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Practice in this laſt War was, to the Diminution of the Honour that belongeth to the Crown of England, and to the general Diſſatisfaction of his Majeſty's Subjects. And de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, That the Chief Commander of the Engliſh Forces under his Majeſty, ſhould be a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97420:12"/>
born in his Majeſty's Dominions: That no</hi> Foreigner <hi>ſhould be of the Board of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or Keeper of the Stores in the Tower of</hi> London: <hi>That, for the Encouragement, of the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>there ſhould not be ſo many ſtrangers Employ'd in the Office of the Ord<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance. That there hath been many Abuſes under Pretence of Preſſing Men for the Fleet; And therefore They humbly Advice, That the Offenders ſhould be immediately Caſhiered, and Proſecuted with the utmoſt Rigour of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HIS Gracious Anſwer was, <hi>That He would conſider of it.</hi> And we may ſuppoſe, That he is conſidering of it ſtill: For he hath not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd one word of it; But on the Contrary, to ſhew the regard he has for all the <hi>Peers</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and for the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> He has acted quite contrary to this <hi>Addreſs,</hi> more ſince, than before: For not only Abroad, in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and in <hi>Savoy,</hi> are the <hi>Engliſh</hi> every where un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Foreign Commanders in Chief:</hi> But, to uſe them as they deſerve, He has now this laſt time, made a <hi>Foreigner</hi> [Scomberge] <hi>Commander in Chief</hi> of all the Forces left in <hi>England</hi> Let the <hi>Lords</hi> Addreſs again! They would if they were <hi>Engliſh Men!</hi> Or if he were an <hi>Hereditary King!</hi> But ſome will bear more Inſults from a <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> than a <hi>Wife.</hi> And a <hi>King</hi> of our own making, Coſts us more than <hi>Twenty</hi> of God's ſending, We think our ſelves bound to Acquieſce in <hi>our own Act and Deed!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any of the <hi>Curſed</hi> and <hi>Rebel Parliaments</hi> could have found a <hi>Gaffney</hi> or <hi>Glenco</hi> againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the 1ſt, or any of his Sons, what a Noiſe would they have made! How had all the World been filled with <hi>Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrances!</hi> What a Diſmal <hi>Idea</hi> would have been Raiſed of <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Government! In the former Reigns, how was the Nation Alarm'd with what was <hi>Whiſpered;</hi> and not <hi>Whiſpered,</hi> or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much as <hi>thought</hi> of, in the King's <hi>Bed-Chamber;</hi> in his <hi>Cloſet!</hi> Of <hi>Secret Leagues,</hi> and <hi>Private Aſſaſſinations</hi> of Men that Murther'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; where there was not the leaſt Umbrage or Colour of Pretence! How Induſtrious was it ſpread and imbib'd by the <hi>Mob</hi> of this Nation, That King <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d. and the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> were both, <hi>Murthered</hi> by the Procurement of one they had a mind to Blacken! And Forty <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Witneſſes of the Greateſt <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> were not ſufficient to make them believe a P. of <hi>Wales;</hi> Tho' not one Man, or Woman in the Nation ever <hi>Depos'd</hi> any thing to the Contrary: Nor was there any other Argument againſt it, beſides a few <hi>Drunken Songs.</hi> But that was enough, becauſe it was againſt a <hi>Lawful King!</hi> And on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, tho' they ſee their Fellow Subjects <hi>Gaffney'd</hi> and <hi>Glenco'd</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Faces; Tho' it be Printed in the <hi>Gazetts,</hi> and Publick <hi>Votes</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> and that the Houſe of <hi>Lords</hi> Print their <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes,</hi> contrary to their uſual Cuſtom, on purpoſe to let the Nation ſee— Yet they will not ſee. No. All this is not NOW ſufficient to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print it one half hour in their Memories, after Reading of the Publick Papers; They neglect it, They forget it, as not concerning them! <hi>Non Perſuadebis, etiamſi Perſuaſeris,</hi> is their Reſolution. And <hi>Quos Perdere vult Jupiter, Dementat,</hi> I wiſh may not be their <hi>Fate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:97420:13"/>BUT to bring our Story to an End: There is One Noble Stroke of of Secretary <hi>Johnſton</hi>'s behind, Whereby he thinks he has wiped his Maſter clean, from all Imputation of the Maſſacre of <hi>Glenco;</hi> And that is, He has perſwaded Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Hamilton</hi> (whoſe Order to <hi>Duncanſon</hi> is in the foreſaid Natrative) to <hi>Abſcond</hi> for ſome time; and then to ſlip over to K. W. in <hi>Flanders;</hi> which he has done. This ſhews as if he were more Guilty than the reſt. He is made the <hi>Scape-goal,</hi> and all this Sin laid upon his Head. But if <hi>Hill</hi> gave his Orders to his Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Hamilton</hi> (which he Avers in his Order to <hi>Duncan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>) Why was it more Criminal in <hi>Hamilton</hi> to hand down his Collonel's Orders to the next Subaltern?</p>
            <p>AND why muſt <hi>Glen-Lyon,</hi> and the others who actually Committed that Horrid <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> and are now in their Reſpective Commands in <hi>Flanders,</hi> Why ſhould theſe be Excuſed?</p>
            <p>O! No! They are not excuſed, for as in the Gazette 18th <hi>July</hi> 1695. The Parliament in <hi>Scotland</hi> has made a fierce <hi>Vote</hi> againſt them, viz. <hi>That his Majeſty be Addreſs'd to ſend them home to be proſecuted for the ſame, Or Not? As his Majeſty ſhall think fit.</hi>— OR NOT! This is as Civil as Heart could wiſh! And whether this <hi>Addreſs</hi> was ſent, <hi>or Not;</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was truſted to Secretary <hi>Johnſton</hi> to ſend it, <hi>or Not,</hi> is all One: For inſtead of ſending them Home to be Tryed, <hi>Hamilton</hi> is ſent to them; And in Juſtice we are to ſuppoſe that Due Care will be taken, That in this Campaign, They ſhall either be <hi>Killed, Taken,</hi> or <hi>Deſert.</hi> And then if we had them again, How we would Hang the Rogues.</p>
            <p>BUT our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament was much more <hi>Complayſant</hi> to their <hi>Verianus</hi>'s; they did not put them to the trouble ſo much as of a <hi>Sham Abſconding</hi> for a little time; No, nor of ſuffering the leaſt <hi>Diſgrace</hi> for their more Solemn and Judicial <hi>Murther:</hi> But Commanded them to take their Places again in their <hi>Senate-Houſe;</hi> Thus doing them Honour, for their Noble Breach of our <hi>Laws;</hi> And ſignifying to the <hi>Nation</hi> what <hi>Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications</hi> are Expected in thoſe whom they Chooſe to <hi>Repreſent</hi> them; and in whoſe hands they have Depoſited the <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-Account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> Diſpoſal of their <hi>Eſtates, Lives,</hi> and <hi>Liberties!</hi> At leaſt, it is ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. And the <hi>Silence</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> in this Caſe, is taken for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97420:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
